Chapter 98. Stowing down and clearing up.
Already it has been related how the great Leviathan is a far off described
from the mast head. How he is chased over the watery moors and slaughtered in
the valleys of the deep. How he is then towed alongside and beheaded. And how on
the principle which entitled the headsman of old to the garments in which
the beheaded was killed, his great padded serto becomes the property of his
executioner. How in due time he is condemned to the pots, and like
Shadrach, Mishach, and Abednego, his spermicetti, oil, and bone pass
unscathed through the fire. But now it remains to conclude the last chapter of
this part of the description by rehearsing, singing, if I may, the
romantic proceeding of decanting off his oil into the casks and striking them
down into the hold, where once again Leviathan returns to his native
profoundities, sliding along beneath the surface as before, but alas never more
to rise and blow. While still warm, the oil, like hot punch, is received into
the six barrel casks. And while perhaps the ship is pitching and rolling this
way and that in the midnight sea, the enormous casks are sued round and headed
over end for end, and sometimes perilously scoot across the slippery
deck like so many landslides, till at last manhandled and stayed in their
course, and all round the hoops wrap wrap go as many hammers as can play upon
them. For now, exeicio, every sailor is a cooper.
At length, when the last pint is casked, and all is cool, then the great
hatchways are unsealed, the bowels of the ship are thrown open, and down go
the casks to their final rest in the sea. This done, the hatches are replaced
and hermetically closed, like a closet walled up.
In the sperm fishery, this is perhaps one of the most remarkable incidents in
all the business of whaling. One day the planks stream with freshets of blood and
oil. On the sacred quarter deck, enormous masses of the whale's head are
profanely piled. Great rusty casks lie about as in a brewery yard. The smoke
from the triworks is besuited all the bullwarks. The mariners go about
suffused with anxiousness. The entire ship seems great Leviathan himself,
while on all hands the den is deafening.
But a day or two after you look about you and prick your ears in this
self-same ship, and were it not for the telltale boats and triworks, you would
all but swear you trod some silent merchant vessel with a most scrupulously
neat commander. The unmanufactured sperm oil possesses a singularly cleansing
virtue. This is the reason why the decks never look so white as just after what
they call an affair of oil. Besides, from the ashes of the burned scraps of
the whale, a potent lie is readily made, and whenever any adhesiveness from the
back of the whale remains clinging to the side, that lie quickly exterminates
it. Hands go diligently along the bull works, and with buckets of water and
rags restore them to their full tidiness. The soot is brushed from the
lower rigging. All the numerous implements which have been in use are
likewise faithfully cleansed and put away. The great hatch is scrubbed and
placed upon the triworks, completely hiding the pots. Every cask is out of
sight, all tackles are coiled in unseen nooks. And when by the combined and
simultaneous industry of almost the entire ship's company, the whole of this
conscientious duty is at last concluded, then the crew themselves proceed to
their own ablutions, shift themselves from top to toe, and finally issue to
the immaculate deck, fresh and all a glow, as bridegroom new leaped from out
of the daintiest Holland.
Now with a ladated step they pace the planks in twos and threes and humorously
discourse of parlors, sofas, carpets and fine camrics proposed to mat the deck.
Think of having hanging to the top object not to taking tea by moonlight on
the piaza of the folks. To hint to such musk mariners of oil and bone and
blubber were little short of audacity.
They know not the thing you distantly allude to. away and bring us napkins.
But mark aloft there at the three mast heads stand three men intent on spying
out more whales which if caught infallibly will again soil the old oak
and furniture and drop at least one small grease spot somewhere. Yes, and
many is the time when after the severest uninterrupted labors which know no
night, continuing straight through for 96 hours, when from the boat where they
have swelled their wrists with all day rowing on the line, they only stepped to
the deck to carry vast chains and heaved the heavy windless and cut and slash.
Yay, and in their very sweatings to be smoked and burned a new by the combined
fires of the equatorial sun and the equatorial triworks. When on the heels
of all this they have finally burred themselves to cleanse the ship and make
a spotless dairy room of it. Many is the time the poor fellows just buttoning the
necks of their clean frocks are startled by the cry of there she blows and away
they fly to fight another whale and go through the whole weary thing again. Oh
my friends, but this is mankilling yet this is life. For hardly have we
mortals, by long toilings, extracted from this world's vast bulk its small
but valuable sperm, and then with weary patience, cleansed ourselves from its
defilements, and learn to live here in clean tabernacles of the soul. Hardly is
this done when, there she blows, the ghost is spouted up, and away we sail to
fight some other world, and go through young life's old routine again.
Oh, the matmpsicosis.
Oh, Pythagoras that in bright Greece 2,000 years ago did die, so good, so
wise, so mild. I sailed with thee along the Peruvian coast last voyage, and
foolish as I am, taught thee, a green, simple boy, how to splice a rope.